[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software this is when you want for
software engineering radio today I have
with me Mike Baca who is an Rd
programmer and form a head of software
MX the London multi acid exchange
Michael is an active Java community
members including sporadic contributions
to open-source projects like gnu
classpath JBoss mono and lives now in
new zealand working remotely for MX
today I will be talking with Mike about
the MX architecture Mike welcome to the
show yeah thank you thank you saying did
I forget to mention anything important
about you I think one of the main the
only anyone in terms of the open source
thing is the main thing I do my in the
open source space at the moment is
maintain the olmecs disruptor I'm sure
we'll probably talk about that
okay um let's start just for some
context setting what is MX and Betfair
okay so bit fear it's the first this
we're starting with bit fear because
it's a fairly important part of our
history bit fear is a peer-to-peer
sports betting platform so bidding on
things like horses and football and that
sort of thing and they had a project
quite a few years ago now before I was
involved with with Lmax where they
wanted to experiment with building a
very much higher performance exchange
something sort of 100 times faster than
what they currently have because sports
betting exchanges in financial exchanges
from a technical perspective are
actually quite similar you have the
concept of prices and quantities and
matching people based on odds in a
betting system or prices based in the
finance system so they launched sort of
a research project that carried on and
they then they made some interesting
discoveries around how an exchange
should work and they decided to take
some of the ideas from there and
launched a company called trade fear
which was the idea of building you know
but you know so a foray from from
betting into finance so they took a lot
of the ideas from those that research
project but none of the actual code and
built what would eventually become the
Omax exchange after a period of time we
really branded to move what move away
sort of from the other trade fear name
trade fair bit fear have actually cents
and sold their controlling ownership of
Lmax
a few years ago there was a management
buyout by the CEO so Lmax are sort of
more independently owned now I believe
bit fest will have a share but it's
largely owned by the CEO and the staff
now okay can you name it took me good
business case for air mix for the next
what is an order yeah okay so probably
worth explaining what we do what lmax is
I kind of missed in the initially
explanation so we we set the goal of
building a it's called a CFD it's a
contract for difference type financial
exchanges where you trade pretty much
any sort of asset that can be things
from options futures FX on margin so
these are emerging products you're not
paying the full amount but it's
essentially a derivative and we've
actually ended up evolving to be much
more focused on the foreign exchange
space so Lmax itself runs an ethics
exchange and we actually do that for a
number of different market sectors we
have what we call a professional
exchange which is largely brokers and
you know one of the individuals we have
an institutional exchange which is for
more the hind trading and we also have
an interbank exchange which is
exclusively for banks so to give a bit
of background on how an exchange works
there's a couple of terms which seem to
be fairly common across the across the
industry so we have the concepts a few
concepts that we'd like to talk about we
have instructions we have orders and we
have trades any of executions so the
first offer somebody will sing to
something in the form of a message which
says I would like to place an order or
I'd like to cancel an order we turn
these as instructions so the messages
are we sieve from our various customers
and vendors
our instructions when they arrive at the
exchange they will execute and they
create what we call an execution an
execution is just something that's
happened inside of the exchange and as a
result of that execution we can either
create an order or we could be
cancelling and removing an order so in
order is an entity that lives inside the
exchange that has typically some kind of
price and a quantity it the price can be
optional and that so those orders will
then some will live in the exchange for
a period of time some may execute
immediately and as those orders are
created and destroyed we send send back
out to their users execution reports the
interesting bit is the orders themselves
so if you put an order if you paid send
an instruction to place an order with a
specific price in a quantity it will go
on to the order box it will live there
and it will have a price and our
exchange is responsible for ordering
these these orders based on the time
that they've arrived at the exchange and
the price that was placed so the idea is
that the orders to buy would be ordered
by the highest price offered first and
the orders to sell would be ordered by
the lowest price first so the idea is
you're looking constantly at the best
price in the market and then as soon as
we receive an order where the two prices
would match each other so you've got a
buy order and a sell order where the
prices are the same or would overlap
that's when we actually essentially
exchange in our case foreign currency
but it could be money for some sort of
commodity and that's when a trade occurs
so that's when you actually have the
concept of a trade which involves the
two parties exchanging something so
those are probably the the five main
concepts we have in a financial exchange
okay what are the main non-functional
requirements you have to face I can
imagine
scalability because it's an open trading
platform the the most important is a
service level agreement we have is
around response time so within a
financial exchange the biggest concern
or whenever the big concerns our
partners in our customers have is around
the concept of risk is and the biggest
factor with regards to risk there our
exchange puts on on their trading is the
time that it takes for us to respond to
an order so if they send us and us an
instruction saying you want to play
in order for this amount and we can
respond to them in a very short period
of time with yes your orders been place
it's now on the market at this price if
that's short and predictable it reduces
the amount of risk that they're exposed
to especially for in regards to some
event happening in the Mart and out in
the you know after the the larger market
that they can then place a new order
into the market and move their price or
cancel an existing price okay and be be
confident about that sort of round trip
time so our key SLA is around latency
trying to keep that as low as possible
when we started out we were aiming for a
goal of about a millisecond being our
typical late typical response time the
interesting thing is that was about six
or seven years ago and over time the
entire market has moved and we're
chasing have been chasing lower and
lower latencies it seems to a stop now
we have a typical latency much closer to
100 microseconds now well I know yeah
it's quite a shift you know a factor of
10 in terms of our goals your latency of
the applications I work with is like I
don't know 100 milliseconds 50
milliseconds so yes it's it's quite it's
it's a different sort of a game it's a
very interesting game it's one of the
one of the reasons I really like working
for a financial exchange as it exposes
you to a whole different suite of
problems that you possibly never
considered before and it forces you to
understand a lot about what's going on a
lot about the operating system the
hardware and the software platforms that
you're using the the virtual machines
the standard libraries the compilers all
that sort of thing end up having to
learn a whole lot more than you wouldn't
really have learnt otherwise yeah I had
a look at the disruptor code then I was
like okay wow that is a that's another
world but we come back to that one
before you you you wrote the the
disrupter did you try out any other
technology I mean if I hope here about
financial exchange I immediately think
oh probably they sorted with Erlang or
with a cow or something like that
did you did you evaluate other
approaches and if yes how did you do the
benchmarks I was
I wasn't really involved in that that
was in the project that bit feared to
experiment with different forms of
exchange that exchanges there was a lot
of experimentation in those areas they
looked at you know everything from sort
of you know using database you know
hammering a database there was I leave
Erlang prototypes
there was off-the-shelf prototypes there
was I think you know IBM was involved at
one point so they were there they ran
with a number of different prototypes
and a number of different sorts of
systems as to how the benchmarking was
done I can't really comment because I
wasn't there at the time but the
interesting learnings that came out of
it was one if you want it to be fast you
need it to be in memory so the idea that
you have your data in one but if you
think about like a typical web
application that you might have built
when we were doing this experimentation
so talking about sort of 10 years ago
people would typically approach a java
application with having a database so
MySQL or an Oracle or something like
that and then they would have a web tier
with some business logic in it and then
they'd possibly use an ORM or a mapping
tool so you've got your business logic
with some sort of representation of your
domain objects and then you've got your
database representation and you're
transferring backwards and forwards and
my boss actually had this great
description of that it's a bit like
trying to eat your dinner with a pair of
chopsticks through a letterbox it's you
know you've got your data all the way
over in one place your logic all the way
over in another place and it's actually
sort of one but it's almost universally
true that the faster you want to make
something is the more you co-locate the
executing code with the data itself
and--but for your head actually
experience with doing that with for
their system is very heavily oracle
database based and they ended up moving
a lot of their logic into store
procedures to bring the logic close to
the data ok that's sort of cost of going
backwards or forwards between between
what's executing and when the actual
data is stored the ideas that they
gathered for the omics exchange was to
bring the data up closer to the logics
and move it up to a running and with a
system where the system of record is
actually in memory mmhmm yeah we come
back to that in in depth
yeah maybe before we do that I was
wondering about the context of the MX
system so who are the main users and
what are the the systems it communicates
with the biggest exchange rate one is
professional exchange and we have two
types of market participant in there and
the first one is what we call a market
maker and the idea with market makers in
a financial market is there as an
exchange we've got a responsibility for
having an orderly market we have to make
sure that if the market happens to be
going in a bad direction there's always
a liquidity there for people to trade
against there's always prices and
quantities if somebody's bought
something and the prices going down we
want to make sure that they can actually
sell to get you know to realize their
loss without losing you know absolutely
everything so part of doing that is
having a group of market makers who will
put what they call a two-way price they
put both buy and sell prices into the
market there are those market makers
some of the big bank names that you've
probably heard of you talk about Goldman
Sachs JP Morgan City Bank Westpac those
larger scale banks on the other side we
will have the people that are
essentially trading against those prices
and also with each other the difference
between the two is that the market
makers we won't do any significant risk
controls for the our main professional
users will come through our broker in
which case they will deposit money with
us we will have a relationship with sort
of an external clearing system like a
prime broker or a Clearing House and
when they when they're trading we will
be monitoring how much they're spending
what particular orders they have in the
market whether those are making money or
losing money and if they are losing too
much money we will kick in various risk
controls to to close them out so they
don't lose every single thing every
single thing they have so those are
those those are probably the two main
people we interact with in terms of what
our system communicates with we have
open api's for these customers to come
and communicate and they come over a
variety of different ones we've got so -
a web-based wrist like API which also
has a user interface on top of it and
then we have
Fix api's which if you've not worked in
the financial industry you probably
would have never heard of fix but it's
one of those ones that's used all over
the finance industry hmm it's a socket
connection oriented protocol
unlike HTTP which is connectionless so
you open up a connection you log in and
you stream sort of two-way full-duplex
instructions up and execution reports
back and both types of market
participant have slightly different but
both are able to connect the system
using fix and the other main area their
assets and communicates with is the
people that are essentially doing the
clearing for trades so when in a trading
platform people will come they'll buy
they they'll sell those think that stuff
actually really only exists as sort of
ones and zeros and all of the
information about that trading that's
occurred will actually go off to a set
of third parties and the effects
industry we call these prime brokers
financial sectors will cover things like
clearing houses we will send all of the
trades that have occurred out to prime
brokers or clearing houses and what they
will do is at the end of the day they
will basically figure out who owes who
what amount of money so if you imagine
somebody who bought something for a
million dollars then sold it for a
million dollars then bought something
else eventually all of that stuff will
knit off and there may only be a very
small amount of real money that has to
move between move between the various
parties involved in their trading so
those are sort of the three main touch
points then our system has clearing and
a various market participants and
there's a large number of smaller touch
points that we have we've got systems
for running payments we've got systems
for doing credit checking and
authorization and figuring out who our
customers are and CRM touch points
because we use via Salesforce rather
than on our own platform so lots of
others little other small integration
points there any sort of large-scale
business something has to deal with yeah
Amex itself what are the the main
components and can you explain them very
briefly and we go deep later on yep
yep so the the the two main parts we
talk about are the broker in the
exchange the exchange is the bit that I
sort of talked a little bit about
earlier that's primarily responsible for
receiving instructions managing orders
and matching orders to create trades the
second significant part of our system is
the broker and the brokers responsible
for managing risk so we run a a
real-time margining system inside of our
our broker so that's monitoring what we
call positions so that's if somebody but
if you go out and buy something you've
been you know a thousand dollars buying
carrots you currently now have a
position on carrots if the price of the
carrots goes up and down then you are
basically in profit or loss the brokers
job is to track all of that information
and figure out you know how much you are
earning or losing and then doing the
appropriate actions based on their it
also handled things like charging
Commission's which is how we make money
as a business those are the two main
components there is a couple is a whole
bunch of sort of exhilarating that forth
the back of that so off the back of the
exchange we have a system called trade
reporting that's for extending all of
the trades out to the various clearing
destinations we have systems for
historic market data or market
surveillance so as a market runs as
people are trading you need to be able
to watch what's going on we have
specific market operations people for
doing that and their job is to one make
sure that the market is orderly make
sure there's nobody doing nasty insider
trading or prearranged trading or money
laundering so there's lots of tools for
analyzing the market as it's executing
and also going back into the past and
investigating anything that happened if
there's a customer query or even if
there's something a regulatory that
crops up and it in there's sorry you'd
go in then there's numerous other parts
of the system for managing a lot of our
sort of crud style data managing our
instruments managing your customers
managing our user accounts we have kind
of a micro services architecture
although some people might look at it
not really call it micro services but we
have around about 40 different services
running of which like the broker is one
the exchange is one and then sort of a
larger number of supporting services for
doing very you know all those various
types of operations
mmm and the the input disrupter and
output disrupt business logic professor
a processor how do they fit into that so
L services come in a bunch of different
flavors we've got we've got three main
types of service we have what we call a
gateway so that's something that will
sit on the edge of our system and talk
you know a protocol like fix or to the
web or something else like we had ones
that do email and there are other things
we have what we call general services
these are things that will talk to
databases so those are largely managing
crud type operations you've seen them a
message they all store or query
something from a database for you and
then we have what we call our core
services and these are essentially the
broker and the exchange and these are
the ones that are built using their
architecture of having the two -
disruptor that sort of disrupt appear
they will receive messages they will
persist all of their state using this
journaling approach run a single
threaded business you know a single
business logic thread five messages in
as the business logic executes they will
see messages out in response okay that
approach is pretty novel compared to -
most of the well-known architectural
styles addressing properties like low
and predictable latency execution high
throughput and so on
it is mostly driven by mechanical
sympathy we had an episode on soft
engineering radio about it but can you
briefly say explain what mechanical
sympathy means what it is yeah it's it's
yes it's a term that Martin Thompson
sort of applied a lot to software but it
comes originally from from Formula One
racing yeah sir Jackie Stewart coined
the term and the idea is about from that
coming from the sort of the original
racing terminology it's not there a
developer or a Formula One driver needs
to know everything about building and
assembling a car or everything about how
to construct a computer and write an
operating system and construct hardware
but the developer or Formula One driver
needs to have a degree of sympathy or a
degree of understanding of how it works
and especially understanding how it
works best what type of operations do
CPUs work well worth what type of
operations don't they work well with to
give a simple example would be something
along the lines of understanding how the
cache architecture works so in a CPU
there's three main ways that a CPU
architecture tries to optimize memory
access it looks to optimize memory
operations that have what happened
around it at the same time sort of a
temporal optimization so if you are
accessing the same thing within within a
short period of time after accessing it
previously there's a chance that there
will be very fast because there's a high
probability that's going to be in cache
there's spatial locality so this is the
idea that things that are located close
together in memory if you access them
you're actually looking far more likely
to get higher get better throughput as
you as there's a high probability that
things closer together are likely to be
more likely to be in cache and there's
also things like striding so if you've
got consistent access patterns like
linear access to data then there's a
higher likelihood that the CPU will pick
up that striding information be able to
prefetch some of that data throw into
cache if you're doing something like
very scattered random access over a very
large memory space you'll find that that
those type of operations are much slower
than sequential access over smaller
regions of memory and so these are you
don't really need to understand exactly
why those things work that way but
having a degree of sympathy the fact
that things do work that way and being
able to experimentally determine which
one works and which one doesn't allows
you to design software that's going to
work better on your computer rather than
or better on the systems that you deploy
rather than worse hmm if I if I look at
the process of cache what is what's the
order of magnitude I'm faster if
everything is happening in if all my
data in the l1 cache compared to random
access so there's some I don't the exact
numbers in front of me but accessing
something in l1 cache you are looking at
only only one one zero one two three CPU
cycles if you're going all the way out
to main memory you could be looking
something in the region of 200 CPU
cycles so that's a factor of 200 between
main memory and lol l1 cache between l1
and l3 l3 tends to be about something
like 40 to 60 cycles so even between l1
and l3 you are still looking at you know
quite a large factor of difference you
know in fact the factor of 40 so there's
this actually some really interesting
research work on looking at this sort of
stuff in the abstract sense as well
certainly one that I area I've only just
started delving into is this concept of
cache oblivious algorithms and this is
the idea of saying well okay we've got
these cache hierarchies and they're vary
from machine to machine but the idea of
cache oblivious algorithms as they've
come up with a a model or a sort of a
theoretical model of a cache hierarchy
and some so mathematics or a calculus
where you're not analyzing algorithms in
terms of sort of order in in terms of
number of operations but actually the
idea of having essentially two layers of
cache with one as fast as one is slow
and the cost of the algorithms and
number of times you have to go to that
slower store and there's some kind of
interesting mathematics around there and
some interesting studies of algorithms
in that area showing how the you know
understanding that sort of cache
hierarchy from an abstract level has
allows you to design algorithms that
will work faster on real Hardware where
did you were and how did you implement
that the the cache oblivious algorithms
yeah yeah well it's more justify that
definitely has more being an idea an
area of research so there's actually a
fair amount of stuff in the academic
space around there but even things like
em sequentially accessing an array is an
idea of cache oblivious algorithm the
idea is you're making the assumption
that there's a the cache hierarchy will
have some sort of striding of support
for optimizing prefetching when you're
striding so that's kind of one very
simple example of applying a cache
oblivious algorithm is that if you have
an array of data and you want to do
something on it you know going to learn
nearly in a linear fashion through that
array rather than a random access I mean
rather than going random access through
that array will give you a better result
mmm talking about an array we wanted to
talk about the disrupter yeah
what is the disrupter can the disruptor
is a small library that we wrote for
doing very fast passing of messages
between threads so when we first started
probably worthwhile going a little bit
back to the original Lmax architecture
when we started out so the the idea is
when we when we did the research around
how to best build an exchange the main
learning was as we wanted to build a
system that was mostly holey running in
memory as its form of system of record
in order to make that work efficiently
you still have to have some way of
actually storing the data because you
can't just have everything only a memory
because what happens a few switch the
Machine off the data needs to be stored
somehow hmm
so the fairly simple approach was to
simply take all of the messages that
were flowing into the system store them
in a persistent journal sequentially and
then if we have some sort of crash or we
need to restart the Machine we have some
known initial state in the form of a
snapshot which we load up and then we
replay the messages back into the system
in the same order that they were applied
originally returning us back to the same
state obviously to make that work
correctly is a couple of constraints you
need to have things along the lines of
determinate deterministic execution you
have to avoid things like calling system
current time milliseconds or you're
using any sort of random number
generators with non fixed seeds that
type of thing to make sure that when you
replay your messages into the system you
get back to a consistent state so you
know taking this architecture we end up
with a very sort of asynchronous system
which is sort of messages and messages
out but we wanted to have these various
parts of the system the business
processing the journaling also the other
thing we wanted to do was have high
availability so have you know
secondaries which would receive the same
stream of events and be able to actually
have the same data set in memory in the
same state to handle failover so we were
sending messages out to secondaries
we're sending messages off to a journal
and we're doing business logic
processing and we wanted these three
things to happen concurrently but we
needed sort of an ordering order
dependencies between these so he wanted
journaling and replication to a
secondary to happen completely in
parallel we didn't need one of those to
wait for the other but we needed both of
those things to fit
before we would take a given message and
process it because that way we wouldn't
update our state with stats any messages
out until we knew we had secured those
messages in another system or journaled
low and journaled locally so that sort
of the the guarantees that we wanted to
provide and our our initial architecture
use just standard Java cues so the ones
that you would find inside that the side
the standard JDK so the idea we would
send a message to the journaling system
that was seen a message to the
replication system once the message we
replicated seemed to message on to the
business will object which will then do
the work this I think has often been
described as sort of a cedar
architecture I think it sort of dates to
you know a couple of decades the codes
now but the the disadvantage of their
architecture is everything was
sequential and we really wanted to take
the journaling and the replication and
run those two things in parallel and we
found that because those that were the
two most expensive stages of the system
the business logic itself ended up being
very fast when you're running completely
in memory you using reasonably well up
the most data structures you've thought
about your business model reasonably
well and you've got some fairly decent
code yes your business logic ins up
being quite quick and you weren't paying
all the cost in terms of this journey
the journaling game and replication so
what we found we wanted was something
that wasn't point-to-point like a queue
is where you have a single you know a
producer and a consumer and message
comes anything gets consumed on the
other side what we actually wanted was
something that's more like a topic and
Jamie so the idea is that when you've
seen the message in you can have
multiple subscribers to that whatever it
happens to be that particular data
structure so that they get that message
in and in a sort of a multicast fashion
and so that's probably the key
difference between something like the
disruptor which is moving messages
between threads and queues that are
moving messages between threads is that
you're sending messages and then you're
multicast in them out to a number of
receivers so that allowed us for to have
the the jailer and the replicator
running in parallel because they would
simply connect to the ring buffer and
message we go into the ring buffer and
then those two those two threads would
see the message at the same time through
the same piece of work the other
interesting feature that's built into
the disruptor is the notion of a graph
of dependencies so this is the second
feature that we wanted as we wanted to
be able to say okay I don't want to do
the business logic until I know
the replication and the journaling has
already occurred and we do this through
sequence numbers so every message that
flows through the disruptor is unique
Lisa's a uniquely sequenced in a strict
a sending order and then each one of the
consumers on the ring buffer will then
have its own sequence which will
indicate what miss em you know what
messages it's processed and then
disruptor allows you to set up the
consumers such that you can say okay
this consumer here and listen this case
our business logic I want you to be
gated on these other two so all that
will all that means they will see you to
see the messages coming off the ring
buffer in the same fashion at the other
consumers will but it will stop and wait
for those other consumers to have
processes they process their messages
first which involves their sequence
numbers ticking up and as soon as that
gated processor sees those messages
moving or sees those sequence numbers
moving it can then go ahead and
processes and process the messages so
this reduced amount of copying you know
with with a queue type of implementation
you're copying data in and out of all of
these threads allowed us to take these
expensive operations and run them in
parallel and also allowed us to have the
sort of you know graph of dependencies
and allow us to put constraints on when
things would actually occur based on
based on what have been processed before
in order to give us sort of our give us
our reliability guarantees and the the
the ring buffer is it's just a simple
object array is that that you pre feel
curing start up is that true yes that's
correct the interesting thing about the
disruptor in the work I did in version 3
is that we actually managed to
completely separate the ring buffer or
the store of data from all the code that
does allow concurrent work so
interestingly you can actually use the
disruptor is almost like a generic
sequencer so the default implementation
is a ring buffer provided is you provide
a factory object per set to this
disruptor disruptor will initialize a
ring buffer of objects and then
initialize them all using that factory
constructor so a pre build a whole bunch
of objects then when you place messages
into the disruptor you can actually
reuse the objects inside of inside of
the inside of the array mm and that has
something to do with mechanical sympathy
yes if you do that yes sir the
original reason was there once we did a
lot of this optimization once we've you
know once we built the disruptor got rid
of all the locks we can talk about sort
of lock free stuff in it in a minute and
you know had the journaling working fast
and replication working well our biggest
cost in terms of response times was
garbage collection and yeah I think just
about anybody's worked in any managed
environment understands the cost of
garbage and so we wanted to be able to
say I want this thing if I so decide to
not create any garbage so this that was
a whole point we wanted to be able to
have it work in a garbage free way so
that was some of the reasons for doing
the pre allocation but you don't have to
do pre allocation so this is one of
these things it's optionally garbage
free but the interesting thing about the
ring buffer is you can also put your own
data structures in there as well and why
is it garbage free because I I pre
initialize it and yes of all the objects
are pre created so you create them all
and then you so for what we do is we
have a small object in there that
represents a message it has some header
information on this object and then a
byte array at the end of it
so as we receive our data off the wire
we will simply grab the mission's that's
currently sitting the objects Camry
sitting in the disruptor and then copy
the bytes that we received off the
network into the byte array that's
already been pre allocated inside the
disruptor so on the networking side
we've got a buffer that we're reusing so
we just pass it into our networking
calls we get some data back and then we
copy the data into this pre-allocated
array inside of the disruptor which then
gets passed on to the business logic
thread so all of those buffers are all
pre created and just simply being reused
so during that operation there's no
actual allocation at all so in therefore
no garbage creation okay and the the
sequence counter yeah can you explain
what it what it does and its
relationship to memory barriers and
memory fences so this is where we start
to get into the the lock-free and
non-blocking algorithm side of things so
one of the things that we discovered
when we were looking at queues and we
did a fair bit of research into the
various types of queues inside the JDK
and we wrote our own custom queues and
we spent a fair bit of trial time trying
to optimize such
there that we wouldn't run into the lock
you know hit the locks particularly
often what we were trying to do was
avoid lock contention because we found
that actually that was one of our most
significant costs in moving a message
between threads is there if you are
using a standard queue what you will do
is under under the covers they will be a
lock object and then we'll use a
condition variable to signal to awaiting
through that a message is available so
your consumer thread winter into the
lock it will if there's no message is
there it'll grab the signal the
condition object in a wait a signal when
a message is sent into the queue it will
then take out the lock
grab the condition object and signal to
anything listening on that that there's
messages available typically certainly
when we were first started on something
that was slightly already older hardware
we measured that to be somewhere in the
region of about thirty odd microseconds
which in itself is not terrible the
problem was is is the long tail in terms
of latency you would end up with the
situations where it could take as many
as two or even four milliseconds for
that message to make it to the other
thread for that signaling operation to
work because it has to go all the way
down into the kernel the kernel I still
then go find the particular process and
park it bring it up and running it's
gonna have a cold cache it's gonna have
all sorts of other have to do a bunch of
context switching and all that so it's
enough to wait the thread up and started
running again so we found there in order
to get to the system up to the
performance that we wanted to get the
response times out of the system that we
that we required is we also had to make
the disrupter lock free or optionally
lock free so be able to say right I'm
going to sacrifice CPU cycles and power
efficiency in order to gain latency or
response time benefits so the way that
we do there is that we made it such that
all of the concurrent operations in
terms of memory safety and avoiding
memory corruption and making sure things
are correct we're done using lock free
algorithms and it's the sequences
essentially at the core of us and so
inside the Java memory model in actually
most other memory models you have the
notion of happens before happens after
and there are specific instructions in
most languages that allow you to say
right here's a bunch of operations on
some four
of memory now I'm going to do this
particular concurrent operation that
says okay all of those operations now
will occur before this particular
operation and the reason for there is
certainly modern CPUs and modern modern
compilers are allowed to take a few
liberties with the ordering of their of
your code so they look at a bunch of
instructions that you've written and
whatever programming language Java or C
whatever and the compiler or the CPU
might decide that they can actually
start reordering those instructions in
order to get a bit of throughput better
optimizations it may eliminate certain
instructions completely CPUs have things
like instruction level parallelism so
they might have several execution units
and they say okay I see all of those
instructions I've got spare execution
units I'll run all those things in
parallel and they might come back at
different points in time and so the idea
of a memory model is allow you to give
some sort of reasoning or some sort of
control over there to say okay I've sent
this whole bunch of instructions through
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
update some data in our case what we're
talking about is writing data into these
objects that are sitting inside the
disruptor so we're copying bytes off the
network which is setting up some header
fields with some meta information about
this message and all of those operations
can be to a degree reordered and what we
want to make sure happens is when we're
on the receiving side and the consumer
that we don't see partially written
information or corrupted information
information it might you know not yet
have arrived so what we do is once we
filled the message up with the data that
we want we then increment the sequence
number and that particular instruction
happens to be what's called a fencing
instruction or a memory barrier so we
use what's called a a store store fence
the idea of a store store fence is if
you've got a whole lot of stores
happening to memory which is what we're
doing we're writing into this various
objects in this row inside a disruptor
we then want to say right at this point
all of the rights to the section of
memory will complete before this one
complete so they're on the consuming
side the very first thing we will do is
then read the sequence number hmm so as
the so if the consumer sees the sequence
number change it knows that all of the
write operations that happen before that
consumer that sequence number
incremented will be visible to it
they're all morally correct they won't
be corrupt so you get the idea that on
the reading side you then have what
that's called a load load fence so I
know that after reading this thing all
of the subsequent reads I do of the data
out of that disruptor won't be reordered
ahead of my first read of the sequence
number so that sequence number the the
right of it is a store store barrier
that prevents any stores happening after
it in the readers what's called a load
load barrier which means none of the
loads that I'm doing if that data will
happen before that load hmm allows you
to get allows for the data to be
transferred correctly between the two
threads okay but you you you you have
only a single writer write to the
tutoring buffer or do you have multiple
writers if you have multiple writers
then you have again contention is that
true that is true we do actually support
both there are often cases where you end
up you you can't get away from the fact
that you might might have multiple
threads in your system or wanting to put
data into the same ring buffer we run
into that in a number of cases we use
for example we actually use a disruptor
in a lot of our different services not
just in our core services so we use it
in our web tier as well and as you
mentioned any sort of web application
you've always got hundreds hundreds of
threads servicing your various web
application with requests having to
write and they're they in our galactic
ation have to write into the same ring
with what we do have is an optimization
for the single writer case so when
you're setting up the disrupter if you
know that in your situation is only over
one thread writing there which is quite
common in some high-throughput network
applications they often use a single
non-blocking i/o networking thread you
can say right I only want to support
single 3d producers and in that case you
will actually often get a better order
of magnitude performance and throughput
out of the out of the disruptor if you
can't make that guarantee then the
default is actually to use the multi
producer case which has a couple of
additional instructions that has to use
a compare and set instruction in order
for the various producers to make sure
they each get an individual slot inside
of the Disrupt so that's a gives a it's
got an additional cost as to to doing
that but one of the advantages
of using the disruptor for those
situations over contingent in general is
it it does the absolute minimum or
certain the minimum that we've been able
to extract out of it
so that the cost of contingent is
brought down to effectively a single
compared and set instruction if you
weren't using something like the
disruptor and you were trying to do all
of these operation you know a whole
bunch of operations in multiple threads
at the same time you would end up with
having to use locks or some other
slightly trickier forms of concurrent
controls and you could end up with much
longer regions where you're actually
contended so the advantage of sticking
everything into the disruptor then
having your King go through to consumer
work very quickly on those events is
your manage to reduce that amount of
contention to a very small amount okay
one thing I found really interesting is
that the the ring buffer size is always
a power of two and that this has to do
with operations offers/buy offered by
process of ports again can you explain
that yeah yeah it's kind of kind of an
interesting one the whole reason for it
is the the the ring buffer is fairly
straightforward simple ring buffers so
the idea is that the ring buffer has
some sort of size and in this the
sequence number increases monotonically
so it won't the sequence number is a
64-bit signed integer it keeps on
increasing as far as it will possibly go
so when I want to put a message into the
into the ring buffer and the typical
operation is you we take our sequence
number and we do a modulo operation we
calculate the remainder and then we
stick the value in at the slot pointed
to by that remainder value a fairly
typical sort of our operation the
difficulty is on an on pair of two value
you have to use a modular operation
which is effectively a divide operation
it's got roughly the same you know it's
basically the same cost as the divide
operation which are particularly slow I
can't remember the exact numbers off the
top of my head but they are tins of
cycles on a modern intel cpu the reason
we use a power of two is that if you're
if you're doing a division your
numerator is actually a power of two you
can do an optimization to do a bitwise
calculation to figure out what there are
may
norbi so you convert the number your
divisor you if you subtract one from
that value sorry it's not your numerator
if your divisor is a power of two you
can subtract one from that value and do
a very fast mask operation on on the
input value and that will give you the
remainder so it only applies if you are
trying to calculate minder for a value
that is a pair of two and then and that
instructions only a single cycle and
pipelines quite nicely fill all the rest
of the things so it's quite a big
difference in performance cost well it's
yeah I mean it's it's so big than effect
even the standard Java hash map that
you're getting to understand at JDK
moves towards power of two based sized
arrays rather than using that yeah often
in in hashmap theory or a hash table
theory people talk about having arrays
and are based on prime numbers because
you get a bit of distribution of
elements but actually the practical
costs of a division operation mean that
using a power of two based array is
actually more efficient and then working
on having a sort of a you know a
statistically better hashing algorithm
to try and get you a better distribution
of remaining table so that's kind of it
that's another sort of interesting piece
of mechanical sympathy you've got theory
suggesting one thing but the actual real
mechanics of the hardware suggesting
something else hmm
yeah there is there is a lot of stuff
which I found really interesting I think
we Martin Thompson also provides a plot
course for he mostly explain these
things in in detail right yes so I would
also publish them in the in the show
notes I want to close with the with a
disrupter and move on to the the
business logic processor and you said a
good domain model is really important
for performance why is that and what is
it what is a good domain model that's an
interesting question is yeah how do you
find how you define good and one of the
reasons one of the interesting things I
learned coming to lmax is and something
something sort of beaten into me a
little bit about working there is how
important modeling the domain is and
it's something I didn't really grasp
until I got there until once you start
thinking about the problem terms of the
way the business uses
and you start having some of those the
important concepts so that's the so that
the distillation part of perhaps the DDD
model once you have the the the really
important concepts represented inside of
your code you're more likely to build
something that's only doing the things
that it needs to do it's kind of a
subtle concept it's kind of hard to give
a really concrete represent
representation or argument for but often
I've I've worked in systems I certainly
built systems where you don't really
have a very true representation of the
domain model in your system and you end
up with your software having to do work
that's not actually related to the
business logic and it has cost so they
sort of the overriding on the overall
theory about having a good domain model
improving performance is that you're
only doing what you actually need to do
in order to solve your business problem
if your code is is well modeled and well
represents that problem it's it's it's a
kind of subtlety that sort of it's quite
hard to sort of give a really strong
example for but it's something I've it's
slowly started materializing after
spending a lot of time working in this
domain so for us what what that does
mean is there inside of our system those
terms I talked about previously about
orders and trades and instructions and
executions and execution and reports
those all have representation as domain
objects in our system so if you're
thinking thinking about right I need to
know where this place order instruction
is I need to know what it looks like and
what it does you can actually search for
those concepts in the code and you'll
find them you can find order objects and
their relationships will actually model
what the you know the business domain
suggests they should be okay and if you
if all your data are close to your
operations that also means that that you
can load it into the process of cache
yes so they that's sort of a lot of
that's about having that sort of a
memory system of record and the really
nice thing about doing that is that we
are able to actually take a very domain
driven approach to what we're doing
because we don't have this additional
cost of say if our persistent store was
a database for example having our
in-memory representation in our database
representation having all the mapping
and all that
stuff we can actually just think about
the domain model and just write objects
that represent it because because
they're in memory in memory
representation is the true record of our
system we can think about those sorts of
things in those terms and if we want to
represent a relationship between objects
it's a very simple representation I just
simply create a field and have a you
know if it's going to be a keyed set
into another set of objects there's a
map there or it's a list or it's just a
direct reference to another object so
representing the types of relationships
you might draw up on a diagram when
trying to design an object model are
very easily represented and type into in
terms your system you're not having to
model these things as database
constraints or anything like that so
that that keeps things quite simple so
it's actually quite straightforward to
take a a domain representation and
actually build it and it looks at the
main class like it let's say a normal
class for instance you use an integer
when you let the JVM allocate memory or
do you do also optimize stuff like
direct memory and location via some misc
unsafe or something like that for our
business logic no we're just using
straight domain objects and so there's
kind of two paths you can go down
there's a lot of people actually moving
towards especially in the finance base
in the high performance space moving
towards basically writing their own
object model system on the top of you
know to reach byte buffers or met by
buffers using unsafe and various types
of operations we did look at that
it may be something we do in the future
one of the reasons that we didn't do
that is we gained the reasons to do that
slowly come down to a garbage collection
so being able to manage your own memory
in the way you want there are some other
advantages around striding and being
able to co-locate objects and I think
layout like that but the key one seems
to come down to garbage collection and
we had a choice a couple of years ago
about how we deal with our garbage
collection problem because it was an
issue actually a few years ago we were
facing we did a fair amount of
optimization and got our system down to
around about 5 milliseconds in terms of
GC pauses inside of our exchange system
and slightly more on some of the some of
the other systems and in the end we
decided to move
and toes all systems zing platform and
this allowed us to simply just keep
using standard Java objects and they've
pretty much eliminated the majority of
our GC pauses we have very rare
occasional 1 millisecond pauses but most
of the time our GC cycles set in the 1
to 200 microsecond range so managed to
take away there's a very significant
cost in terms of our response time and
allow us to keep using some of the
canned modeling objects I think if we
were going to stick with the Oracle JVM
we probably would have had to have gone
the route of using off heap memory
playing with direct byte buffers writing
some of our own memory management for
some of the the core memory core parts
of that domain model that certain side
of our exchange ok I just want to close
the the the disrupter and and the
business logic profit processor and move
to something completely different
ok they file a one of the authors of the
the continuous livery book he also
worked it at MX and I think the book
most of the chapters of the book are
based on work at MX right yes I think I
think I think another chapter book is
based on is you know has many years of
experience both at Thor were send a tell
max and I think a lot of the lot of the
application of continuous delivery was
tried out and experimented and played
with or wallet Lmax mmm so there's one
thing on the unencrypted phille for and
realize them incredibly lucky to have
started at L max and work with somebody
like Dave Farley and loot' an incredible
amount over and the the thing that's
probably the makes sort of our jobs Lots
it much easier is that we started in a
good place
we started with upfront doing
test-driven development acceptance
test-driven development being very
focused on automated interring testing
very focused on ensuring the continuous
integration worked building up the the
various aspects of a continuous delivery
pipeline very early on so adding in
binary repositories building the
deployment tools to make sure our
deployments to our test environments
were as as close to or exactly the same
as our deploy
to our production systems which are all
some of the very key technical practices
that come through with a continuous
delivery which is the the book that he
wrote mmm
so probably you you also have automated
performance test then yes yes we do so
we have about I think I counted about
eight different types of automated tasks
as we've got automated unit tests
integration test acceptance tests
performance tests static analysis
database tests and probably a few others
that I can't remember off the top of my
head but yes we have and we have two
levels of automated performance testing
we have our begin to end performance
tests which take around about 4045
minutes to run there we run up a whole
instance of the system on a set of
hardware which is equivalent to our
production system and we run you know
tens of thousands of transactions per
second through that system and monitor
the the response time over an hour long
period and looking for the individual
outliers to try and find out where out
where our response time goes and we also
have the smaller sort of micro benchmark
style test so we take individual
components that's things like maybe like
our journaler various parts of our
infrastructure various business logic
components and just take them as smaller
classes it's almost like it's like unit
testing for performance and making sure
those individual components are fast as
well so you somehow have then order to
test or the mechanical sympathy so if
the garbage collection starts or not and
things like that yes so the interesting
thing is a lot of what we do in our
interim performance tests is very
similar to what we do in production
because what we would ideally like is
the idea that we can run a do a run
through our performance environment and
there will take in huge amounts of
metrics so we're obviously going to be
measuring inter in transaction times we
capture the transaction time for every
single message flowing through the
system we then try and pull out all
sorts of metrics so obviously things
like garbage collection pause time for
all the different for the services those
messages run through we want to look for
light sees when writing to disk latency
from writing to the network latencies
with inside of our business logic if
we're tripping some sort of you know
some sort of collection has to resize or
this
particular path which has a was
algorithmically bad we want to be able
to find that but we want to be able to
do the same sort of thing in production
as well so we want the same sort of
monitoring information in a performance
environment as our production
environment hmm and that's things we put
a lot of effort into so the way we
actually measure our transaction times
we do it using a tool that's watching
the messages pass through the network
I'm using pcap and sort of
reconstructing those streams and then
just looks for input input the input
message versus the output message it
measures the time difference between
them we have that same piece of
infrastructure running in our production
environment so it allows us to make sure
that when we're measuring we are as much
as possible trying to measure exactly
the same thing in those two environments
okay cool nice is there anything
important I forgot to ask you you want
to mention yeah the game just briefly
back to the continuous delivery thing in
the the automatic acceptance testing so
obviously one of the things we put a lot
of concern consideration in is into a as
a team into as you know around
performance and that sort of thing the
probably the the thing that we soaked
the moat what about the most important
aspect of what we do as a team at Lmax
is probably the automated testing and
the level of automated testing that we
apply one of my sort of slightly
unscientific of a sort of conjectures
and observations is there and we we work
with a very agile team we've instead of
their JA since since the beginning and
what I've noticed is over time we've
just really discarded a many of the
practices we don't have scrum masters
for example we don't do a lot of
estimate estimation we still have we
have Kanban boards but we'd use them in
a fairly light way and a lot of the sort
of the planning and project management
aspects of agile that I've seen are
there to cater for the fact that teams
may not have really strong automated
testing the actually this ability for us
to just make a change put it into our
continuous integration environment and
be really confident that what we're
doing is working and is correct and as
fast and we'll be safe when it goes out
to production allows for a lot of the
other types of project management
features that you may have or you know
another discussion around what gets
released win
and a lot of those sorts of details it
seems to go away you can actually use
all what about in testing sort of paper
over the the cracks if you like of you
know not having certain aspects of your
project management there so I you know
the the key thing for me you know in
terms of owl makes is how well we do
automated testing and how much of a
benefit that brings to us as a team hmm
yeah I I remember they Farley talking
about it and I was really I was really
impressed about all the infrastructure
you guys created an asset how long did
it take to create such an infrastructure
it was just I don't know I mean we just
grew it over time and and now we now you
guys have a really advanced system of
covering everything by tests yeah we I
guess you probably adds that that
question is we will tell you once we're
finished we've yeah we've been building
up on a while and even since you know
David they've done some really excellent
talks about some of the stuff that we've
built
but even subsequent to that we've
continued to build more and more tools
to help us try and understand our
automated tests so one of the biggest
challenges when you're building a lot of
automated tests is giving these
intermittent failures so you'll have a
situation where everything looks correct
but a particular test will fail
sometimes and pass other times and
trying to figure out why that's
occurring can be a real challenge and
that's probably our biggest challenge
now that we have really significant
automated test coverage of our system
it's the squeezing out in the
intermittency and trying to get to these
consistently green builds is where we we
spend most of our effort and iíve done
occasionally done talks on on our
automated testing and a thing that
always to me I was just it really blows
me away and it's it's it's the amount of
effort our team has done to improve
things as I look at this chart over what
we call green builds per month it's a
number of times in a month there are
entire in tweened except in suite test
suite has gone green and when we first
started measuring which was about three
or four years ago that number was in
single digits so it would be a zero or a
one or a two and in the last three four
months those numbers are nine hundred to
a thousand so it's just an amazing shift
and it's it's it's
of effort it really has been a lot of it
we have put a lot of effort into making
it work but the benefits have massively
outweigh outweighed those well those
yeah I can't imagine I mean if you are
totally sure that you can just put
everything into production at any time
yeah it you're not stressed anymore and
I think it's it's really cool yeah it's
an the the other thing is quite good
quite good about it so we have a testing
team as well when you start because
people are not varying as they Farley
people are not very good at for loops
people are smart and creative and
intelligent but they're very bad at
doing the same thing over and over again
and getting it exactly right so if
you're in a situation where you've got
testers and their job is to go through a
test script and repeat the test script
over and over again it's a really poor
use of a person we would much rather
have our testers being creative and
trying to come up with new and
interesting ways to try and break our
system and I think a lot of people in
the industry call this exploratory
testing mmm so this is the other
advantage of having lots of automated
tests as they're our testers can focus
on the interesting bits they can come up
with new and interesting creative ways
to make our system not work and as a
result we can fix those and we can wrap
up tests around those ideas and in terms
you know build up the quality of our
system good thank you Mike for being on
the show that's no problem thank you
very much for having me you know it was
nice I enjoyed it a lot
I want to mention that the feedback of
our listeners is very important so
please help us improving our show and
leave your opinion via Twitter Google+
or LinkedIn this is when you hunt for a
soft engineering
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radio net to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter
at se radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you